

INFORMATION

31 Years old

Montpellier, France

+33 7 52 06 90 74

theophile.mouton92@ gmail.com

ONLINE PROFILES

www.theophile-mouton.com

LinkedIn:

Théophile L. Mouton

Researchgate:

Théophile L. Mouton

Github:

TheophileMt92

LANGUAGES

French

English [

Spanish [

SOFTWARES

- R, Python
- QGIS, ArcGIS
- Git, Github
- Microsoft suite

Théophile L. Mouton

Conservation scientist

I bring a background in macroecology, specializing in biodiversity research. My expertise lies in combining statistical methodologies and geographic information system-based approaches to analyze and quantify changes in biodiversity facing global change. By investigating the underlying processes influencing patterns of biodiversity change, my work has informed the scientific response to the ongoing biodiversity crisis.



WORK EXPERIENCE

2023 - 2024 **IUCN SSC SSG** International Union for the Conservation of Nature Species Survival Commission Shark Specialist Group – Montpellier (remote), France

Postdoctoral Researcher

- Coordinated over 60 scientists for the submission of Important Shark and Ray Areas in the Mediterranean and Black Seas and the Western Indian Ocean Regions.
- Led research on shortfalls in the protection of Important Shark and Ray Areas in the Central and South American Pacific, paper submitted to *Marine Policy*.

2020 - 2023 MARBEC Marine Biodiversity Exploitation and Conservation (Joint Research Unit; CNRS-IRD-Ifremer-University of Montpellier), Montpellier, France

PhD Student

Main project

- Designed and executed a PhD research project in macroecology, formulated scientific hypotheses and compiled and analyzed a large database spanning 30 years.
- Assembled and managed a multinational team of 15 scientists across three continents.
- Published 3 papers in Rank A journals.

Side projects

- Developed R end-to-end pipelines to analyse human population growth within and near protected areas over the last two centuries in the USA.
- Led research on cetacean biodiversity gradients and overlaps with Marine Protected Areas in the Southern Pacific, published in *Biological Conservation*.
- Contributed analyses to a global assessment of elasmobranch functional diversity, published in Nature Communications.

2017 - 2019 **NIWA** National Institute for Water and Atmospheric Research, Hamilton, New Zealand.

Research assistant

- Assisted research projects with statistical programming and GIS tasks.
- Led research on human disturbance impacts on freshwater biodiversity in Waikato Region streams, published in *Science of the Total Environment*.
- Conducted fieldwork in a remote New Caledonia atoll and in New Zealand streams.



EDUCATION

2019 - 2023 University Claude Bernard Lyon I, France

PhD in Macroecology

2014 - 2016 University of Pau and Pays de l'Adour, France

MSc in Dynamics of Aquatic Ecosystems

2011 - 2014 University Montpellier 2, France

BSc in Ecology and Organisms Biology

REFERENCES

Prof. Fabien Leprieur Macroecologist fabien.leprieur@umontpellier.com

Dr. Jonathan TonkinFreshwater ecologist
jonathan.tonkin@canterbury.ac.nz

Prof. Sylvain DolédecFreshwater ecologist
sylvain.doledec@univ-lyon1.fr



Mouton T.L., Gonzalez-Pestana A., Rohner C.A., Charles R., García-Rodríguez E., Kyne P.M., Batlle-Morera A., Notarbartolo di Sciara G., Armstrong A.O. et al. (2024). "Shortfalls in the protection of Important Shark and Ray Areas undermine shark conservation efforts in the Central and South American Pacific." Submitted to: <u>Marine Policy</u>. (*major revisions*)

Mouton T.L., A. Boyé, M. Mclean, J.D. Tonkin, S. Dolédec, N. Bonada, M. Floury, P. Verburg, N. Mouquet, D. Mouillot, F. Leprieur (2024). "Climate change reverses the latitudinal species and trait richness gradients of river invertebrates." Submitted to: <u>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</u>. (major revisions)

Pimiento C., C. Albouy, D. Silvestro, **T. L. Mouton**, L. Velez, D. Mouillot, A. B. Judah, J. N. Griffin and F. Leprieur (2023). "Functional diversity of sharks and rays is highly vulnerable and supported by unique species and locations worldwide." <u>Nature Communications</u> 14(1): 7691.

Mouton T. L., F. Leprieur, M. Floury, F. Stephenson, P. Verburg and J. D. Tonkin (2022). "Climate and land-use driven reorganisation of structure and function in river macroinvertebrate communities." <u>Ecography</u> 2022(3): e06148.

Mouton T. L., F. Stephenson, L. G. Torres, W. Rayment, T. Brough, M. McLean, J. D. Tonkin, C. Albouy and F. Leprieur (2022). "Spatial mismatch in diversity facets reveals contrasting protection for New Zealand's cetacean biodiversity." <u>Biological Conservation</u> **267**: 109484.

Stephenson F., A. A. Rowden, T. Brough, G. Petersen, R. H. Bulmer, J. R. Leathwick, A. M. Lohrer, J. I. Ellis, D. A. Bowden, S. W. Geange, G. A. Funnell, [...] **T. L. Mouton**, et al. (2022). "Development of a Seafloor Community Classification for the New Zealand Region Using a Gradient Forest Approach." <u>Frontiers in Marine Science</u> **8**(792712).

Mouton T.L., J.D. Tonkin, F. Stephenson, P. Verburg, M. Floury (2020). "Increasing climate-driven taxonomic homogenization but functional differentiation among river macroinvertebrate assemblages." <u>Global Change Biology</u>. **00**:1–12.

Stephenson F., J.E. Hewitt, L.G. Torres, **T.L. Mouton**, T. Brough, K.T. Goetz, C.J. Lundquist, A. B. MacDiarmid, J. Ellis, and R. Constantine (2021). "Cetacean conservation planning in a global diversity hotspot: dealing with uncertainty and data deficiencies". <u>Ecosphere</u> **12**(7)

Stephenson F., K. Goetz, B.R. Sharp, **T.L. Mouton**, F.L. Beets, J. Roberts, A.B. MacDiarmid, R. Constantine and C.J. Lundquist (2020). "Modelling the spatial distribution of cetaceans in New Zealand waters." <u>Diversity and Distributions</u> **26**(4): 495-516.

Mouton T.L., F.E. Matheson, F. Stephenson, P. D. Champion, S. Wadhwa, M.P. Hamer, A. Catlin and T. Riis (2019). "Environmental filtering of native and non-native stream macrophyte assemblages by habitat disturbances in an agricultural landscape." <u>Science of The Total Environment</u> **659**: 1370-1381.



SCIENTIFIC REPORTS

Jabado R., P.M. Kyne, E. Garcia-Rodriguez, R. Charles, A.O. Armstrong, **T.L. Mouton**, A. Gonzales-Pestana, A. Battle-Morera, C.A. Rohner (2024). Western Indian Ocean: a regional compendium of Important Shark and Ray Areas. IUCN SSC SSG Shark Specialist Group.

Jabado R., E. Garcia-Rodriguez, P.M. Kyne, R. Charles, A.O. Armstrong, J. Bortoluzzi, **T.L. Mouton**, A. Gonzales-Pestana, A. Battle-Morera, C.A. Rohner, G. Notarbartolo di Sciara (2023). Mediterranean and Black Seas: a regional compendium of Important Shark and Ray Areas. IUCN SSC SSG Shark Specialist Group.

Stephenson F., Goetz K., **Mouton T.L.**, Beets F., Hailes S., Roberts J., Pinkerton M., MacDiarmid A. (2020). Spatial distribution modelling of New Zealand cetacean species. Fisheries New Zealand. New Zealand Aquatic Environment and Biodiversity Report No. 240. 217 p.

Stephenson F, Rowden A., Anderson T., Hewitt J., Costello M., Pinkerton M., Morrison M., Clark M., Wadhwa S., **Mouton T.L.**, Lundquist C.J. (2018). Mapping Key Ecological Areas in the New Zealand Marine Environment: Data collation. Prepared for the Department of Conservation. November 2018

de Winton, M., **Mouton T.L**. (2018) Technical Report on Vegetation Status in Waituna Lagoon: 2009–2018. Prepared for Department of Conservation.